[SPEAKER_00]: A common question that I keep hearing is, you know, why is my existence said to be dukkha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is my life dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean asked by the people who don't necessarily... who think that that's the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is existence... Why is... Why is the existence dukkha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why that suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is meant by that, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Probably talked about it before, but even if I did, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It basically comes down to the possibility of suffering in regard to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You exist means suffering can touch you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not necessarily do so, but the fact that it might, that is suffering in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That possibility that you might suffer at any given time, at any given moment, means your existence is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have a very happy life, never experience any misfortune, nothing like that, which is quite unlikely, but, say, an ideal case scenario, but the fact that at any given
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment of your life you might meet with misfortune or anything that you might find disagreeable, means that possibility, that kind of looming possibility, if you recognize that, you feel unpleasant in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you feel unpleasant in regard to your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, existence is dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's best not to look at that at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, then my existence... Well, no, that's, that's what most people do, because that's just the, the ignorant default response.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just don't look at your exit.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, so many people are afraid of boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like genuinely terrified of being bored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Terrified of not having anything to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Terrified of not having any distraction to keep them, you know, floating on the surface.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then all these things emerge, because they are always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way
[SPEAKER_01]: The way that you can kind of cope, not resolve any issues, but cope, would be to find plentiful distractions, chase your desires like a maniac as much as you can, so that it keeps your gaze diverted from that which is underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is nothing taking your attention away.
[SPEAKER_01]: This weight, this kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: It shows itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't come onto you, because it's actually always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just gets revealed again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can, you can actually, you know, sometimes you have people, you know, my... there's no... my life is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes bad, but generally it's quite all right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I disagree that everything is suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, everything is not suffering in terms of everything is miserable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But everything can be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything potentially causes you suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is suffering in itself on a very subtle level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Subtle, but profound.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, subtle, I don't mean like tiny, insignificant, means deep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even those people, just, just, if, if, if, if they were to be locked in for 24 hours or something, without any distraction, oh, I think they'll quickly change their mind, step forward and want to freak them out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're being, being busy with the things that make you, kind of, that give you pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's like that's an extra extra drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you're busy for various reasons and all kind of merge into this motivation that's rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome because you're being busy, because you basically don't want to look at the problem of your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're finding things to do that you tell yourself are very important and need to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's my duty to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you choose your duties.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, in regard to anything and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do things because, basically, you're running away from looking at your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, being busy keeps you distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, sometimes, well, often, things that you are doing are also providing you with sense pleasure as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that you are distracted initially from the problem, but then you also have pleasure on top of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it gets... you can see how it's easily very intoxicating and then people never look back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because there's always something going on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until there isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until you get sick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until you get old.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you die.
[SPEAKER_01]: It provides the double.
[SPEAKER_01]: The distraction and the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, it proliferates.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more things you do, the more things you create.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more things to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on things you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that initial motivation of being distracted from the problem of existence, that's like a threat.
[SPEAKER_01]: It pertains to whatever you do, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do this, and then, because of that, you do something more, something more, something more, something more, and you spend your whole life doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that threat is in common to all of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how people
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there are cases when people, like, they've been doing things their whole life, working or whatever, and then they get old.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the moment they're not able to physically perform things that their whole life depended on, their mind goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: They lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They go quickly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's an injury or something, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within a week, they're gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't recognize people, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because their whole life it was just depending on that little thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the old age is so hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in the suttas, the Buddha would often... Well, people would come to Buddha and say, yes, indeed, you know, I remember when I, you know, I could catch a galloping horse and I was, you know, prime of my youth, youth and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, I want to put my foot here, but it goes there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want... completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's so hard, because imagine a person who spent their whole life depending on their senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: For this distraction, there was then providing pleasure and so on, to not look at the existence, that was the sole purpose, and now those senses fail.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can't see, you can't hear, let alone provide yourself with manifold pleasures of sights and sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, they're just failing, which means that whole, well, that soul's motivation for pursuing the senses and the distraction and so on, that was provided through that, it's just again there, and now there's no escape from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all people, very often, become very unhappy, even if there's nothing necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just unhappy, miserable, angry, eh... anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... just... just not... not in a good place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't distract yourself anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or...
[SPEAKER_01]: They try to distract themselves with their family and grandchildren and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the joy, the thoughts of my grandchildren.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because nothing, your senses don't provide.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even see them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're blind now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't hear them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, like, again, even more perilous position.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those are completely independent people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when they do something and you do not... Well, that's the exact thing I'm going to bring up now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a... there's a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was looking at some people that... that I know they have a... you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: The father, the mother, their daughter has a child, and now the grandparents are obsessed and completely engrossed in that grandchild, that little girl, and she's the center of the universe, the center of their world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And
[SPEAKER_00]: This provides a major distraction to, you know, everything else is pushed to the side, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense of the air is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all their happiness, and I was looking at some of their photos, all their happiness, they look very happy and excited.
[SPEAKER_00]: The baby is always in the center, literally in the center all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can just see how much their happiness, how much their happiness depends on that child, that little girl.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the things that could go wrong... Oof!
[SPEAKER_00]: If something happens to that little girl, she gets hurt, she dies all of a sudden, you got, you know, you got... you know, these four people's lives are completely, that's done, destroyed, done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they have themselves to blame.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're fully responsible for placing so much importance on that, on that child.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean so much emotional importance for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure you look after it, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But placing so much importance for the purpose of distraction and pleasure and not looking at your own existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, when something does happen, it's... well, it's again... it doesn't suit us.
[SPEAKER_01]: When... when the child dies, you know, they find their own in the streets, distraught, mental, mentally... Where have you gone, my son?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where have you gone?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when it... Buddha says, yeah, that suffering, lamentation, grief, pains, comes from that... those which are dear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that man who's suffering because of his son is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, what are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, when Buddha told him that the family and the children are a source of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the man says, no, no, what are you talking about?
[SPEAKER_01]: They're a source of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he went to another ascetic and some... No, no, he went to the gamblers on the side of the road.
[SPEAKER_01]: The gamblers?
[SPEAKER_01]: People who he saw would... would most likely agree with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they said, no, of course, you were right, the Buddha was wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Queen reported it to the King.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, she had the report to her, then the King said... No, sorry, the King.
[SPEAKER_01]: The King heard that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He went to the Queen, because she was a supporter of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, see, like, I also disagree with the Buddha, because, look, all these children are a source of happiness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then she went to the Buddha, and the Buddha explained, and she went to the King and said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you know your favorite son, your favorite child, if something happens to him right now, that you can't prevent, if he dies, falls ill, would you be... Of course, of course I would be grieving, I would be distraught.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how children are a source of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I mean, you know, it sounds obvious, and it is obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's obvious on a, like, intellectual level, but emotionally, like, that might not mean anything if people are fully attached.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll just, you know, they ignore the fact, because they're already fully dependent upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, ultimately, at the end of the day, that time is going to come when you're dying and you can't have this chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's never... Well, not just that it's not a solution.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a coping, coping mechanism that basically makes things even worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the worse... the harder you're running away from something that you ultimately cannot escape,
[SPEAKER_00]: The harder it will hit you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for most...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, most people don't know that they're running away.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not intentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they're like... Well, it's an act of bad faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're not fully aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason they're not fully aware is because they don't allow themselves to be fully aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They must get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They must be aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... That's exactly... That's why bad faith is that...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an unwholesome attitude, where basically you put...
[SPEAKER_01]: You convince yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in order to convince yourself of such things, you need to know what you convince yourself against.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they basically, through that running away from their resistance, they're carrying that reason for running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't really escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're making it worse, because it becomes implied in everything you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, ultimately, it catches you, as would have always done, because just... And that's why, that's why for many people, sensuality and then giving up sensuality, it's not... it's hard, because it's not just, oh, it's not just that you're giving up pleasure as they come through your senses, but then you're giving up the only means of
[SPEAKER_01]: A sort of escape that you know from that weight of your resistance with impending, kind of looming possibility of suffering, hitting you, landing on you, crushing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why for people, sensuality is not really optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it is optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a matter of choice, but
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not just about pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about having distraction to keep you floating on the top of your resistance, whereby you won't have to look down below.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just, you know, enough space to breathe, but that's about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, for somebody who's now got the idea and is looking
[SPEAKER_00]: All right, my existence is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just like practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seize the value in awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then they have to start going against that old grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Upstream.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, everything, the desire, the senses, the running away, it all falls down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you just... it's easy to give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you recognize that you're just making things worse, now you actually have to stand against that flood and then go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, well, you can imagine how hard that is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you don't have to imagine doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, basically, that's why many people... And, again, because you know that deep down, you know that you are running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, because you're carrying those reasons with you as you're running away, because that's why you're running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you do, eh... if you do, eh... stop and think about going against the grain, then you just realize how hard and heavy that will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that flood will most likely take you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you just carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just pretend and just go down with the flow.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for someone who's got a, you know, like, eh... a grandparent with their granddaughter, they love so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do they...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, theoretically, it's possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But practically, it's pretty much impossible, because they spent 80 years of their life cultivating habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were going with that flood, with the flow, with the distraction, with the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, they got so entrenched now in those directions that
[SPEAKER_01]: There are simply the faculties are not strong enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is not strong enough, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Theoretically, as there were cases in the suttas, the old lady... Do you remember when she had three sons?
[SPEAKER_01]: They married and children, everything, and she and her husband were really well-to-do, and her husband died, and she thought, well, why don't I divide all of our property?
[SPEAKER_01]: And they had a lot of it, and give to my three sons, and they look after me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she did that, and they looked after her in the beginning,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, basically, they were just started, well, being annoyed by her.
[SPEAKER_01]: They didn't like her.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, she would be going to visit one son and she overheard the daughter-in-law saying, oh, well, look, look who's coming again.
[SPEAKER_01]: She has other sons as well to look after her.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is she coming here only?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then she heard that from all of them and got basically completely heartbroken.
[SPEAKER_01]: She was, what, well over 80 probably, given, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: But she couldn't go Pindapad because she was too old.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, she was staying behind cleaning the monastery while the younger nuns were going Pindapad.
[SPEAKER_01]: But she's quite junior.
[SPEAKER_01]: She never met the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But one night, she had one nun.
[SPEAKER_01]: Repeating to another nun what the Buddha said about impermanence, and that, like, one or two lines, she was basically contemplated on, day and night, while she was cleaning, and then at night, she would be doing walking meditation in the corridor.
[SPEAKER_01]: But she was so old, she couldn't walk, so she was leaning on the wall with her hands, and she was walking up and down, and she became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can say, wow, she put... that was so... basically, she put in hard work,
[SPEAKER_01]: After being completely broken by her own family, by her own children, abandoned, basically at the last, the very last stage of life, but that little instruction she got second-hand, she drilled it in deep enough until penetrated ignorance and everything else, and she became an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is possible, theoretically, and in a very
[SPEAKER_01]: Rare cases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Paul, I mean, yeah, well, everyone, you don't have to go and try and let everyone abandon you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just recognize the possibility that that might happen, and that's more than enough to go on in terms of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's the, you know, Nanabir was saying about the vertical view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how to maintain the vertical view and not to run away and hide in distractions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you, as a monk, as someone who's practicing, how do you...?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by developing mindfulness in your day life,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not mindfulness in terms of some kind of weird robotic method, meditation, repetition, noting, but mindfulness in the sense of recognizing intentions behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for as long as you perform a certain action, intention to do that action is there, on a more general level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're mindful of the reasons why you're doing things, why you want to do things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if they're utterly unwholesome, you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's something you have to do, then you reroute it into something that's not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such as eating food, as we discussed before, can be rooted in a very unwholesome, pure sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you contemplate and dwell on it and drill it long enough, you can root it in, no, I'll root it in necessity and I don't care what I eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's, you know, the softest, nicest food or the roughest, because you remain rooted in the necessity of eating food to sustain the body so that you can practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by being aware of your reasons and intentions, you will basically... well, you won't be able to fall into bad faith, you won't be able to fall into that self-deception, and you won't be doing things for the sake of distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how the vertical view is maintained, or, well, developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it will take time to kind of elevate your mind to start looking vertically at the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's been just going, you know, flowing very horizontally with a powerful flow of sensuality and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, you know, people who don't... well, people who haven't been practicing, but they might get the hint of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, say a layperson who
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you can't differentiate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you recognize that you've been doing things for the sake of distraction, then you realize that, well, it feels like whatever you do, it was done because of that distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it most likely was.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that there won't be a point in the future whereby you can then do things that won't be rooted in the distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people sort of can't differentiate and then they try, well, they attempt to throw the whole thing away and then stop doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not... like what I was...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not exercise.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not go out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not go out for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not sit in the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: No projects?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not...
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's impossible because that then becomes your doing of not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you're actively performing and you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're not actually developing mindfulness in regard to the intentions and the actions properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people like that, again, including myself, then, when you see others doing, ah, it's all done for the distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it can be, but not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to know the motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we discussed that before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're in the monastery, you want to go down to the preceptor where the library is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you look why, what, well, where is your intention to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it rooted in the desire to
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe you find some people and other monks there, and have somebody to chat with, because you were actually bored in your room.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you can't admit that to yourself, so then you say, no, I want to go and get some books to read, some good, useful books to read.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the real reason remains rooted in going, hoping to meet people there, to chat for half an hour, and get a bit of entertainment, or whatever I call it, or distracted, just because your room is getting too heavy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, then, if it's rooted in that, you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you still want, like, if you still think, well, no, I do want to get those books, then you make sure you stay focused on the reason, uh, on the wholesome reason for going down to the reception room where the library was to get the books.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even if you do meet other people, well, you won't be entertaining that aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be getting your books and getting back up.
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to, I will not do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will just sit in this room and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will never leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: That still will not re-root your intentions, which means you still remain rooted in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just abstain from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, that should be a default response if you don't know what to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstain from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if in doubt, don't do it, like we're in vinaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting out of doubt, it's a minor offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if actually what you've done wasn't an offense, the fact that you acted out of doubt was a minor offense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean you should actually cultivate that and stay in that doubt for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you should be asking why not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, okay, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm not going to do it, but then I'm going to see why, how, and if you re-root it, then you can do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If... again, when... was it Mahapajapati?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When she asked the Buddha, oh, I'm going for the Vāsa retreat.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to be in seclusion for three months.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me a brief instruction so I can... And he said, whatever you know is unwholesome, abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever you know is wholesome, don't attend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people realize they're kind of entrenched in unwholesome, then they fear everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you're trying to free yourself from unwholesome, but the false response is throwing everything away, including wholesome and unwholesome, everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not do anything ever again, because everything is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is done for the distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything is done because of my ego, my conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's done because of ego and conceit and vanity, if that's where it's rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't root it in those unwholesome things, it won't be done for those purposes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Externally, people might not be able to tell the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll say, oh, look, he's all vain and conceited, arrogant, but they can't tell the difference, because they themselves are rooted in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what they seek.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know, the Buddha himself, he said, when the first man, he met after the life, he said, I am the greatest.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am self-enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody is my teacher.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's factual.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for the man, who himself is a victim of his own conceit and vanity, he said, so be it, my friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rolling his eyes, he left.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking, like, who does he think he is?
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't judge.
[SPEAKER_01]: He couldn't tell.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why there is no...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there is obviously the unwholesome things that cannot be done, like, you know, against the precepts, but in all of the other things in between, things that are not necessarily good or bad, you know, they... they're determined by... by your intention that's behind performing those actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, going to the library,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessarily a bad thing, but it can be a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I want to go on to my sutta study group.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow, that's a very noble thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're going there because you want to be, you know, chatting people up or distracting yourself on the pretext of studying the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, then it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: But many people judge things, well, judge books by its cover.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it requires a degree of wisdom to not do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's universally accepted.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Sutta study group in the monasteries is a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: We all go and do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And probably like 90% of the people might be doing it for completely wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I can vouch because I've witnessed it many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people just go there because it just feels like, hey, we're doing something together, we're partying, just a distraction during the, like, you know, silent retreats or something like that, when there's nothing else happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, this is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you feel justified.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by feeling justified, you mask the fact that you yourself chose
[SPEAKER_01]: To go there for the reasons of distraction or something other unwholesome, but then you you feel justified because externally that is generally accepted as a good thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, good.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm fine then.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're not actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is probably more dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is it all, you know, scholars,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You feel fully justified spending your time, you know, studying etymology and stuff, but not for purpose getting the meaning, but for purpose just becoming a scholar.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you feel, again, oh, you know, spending five days, a few weeks, just printing the random CDs because they're all about the dhamma or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you're doing, you know... Publications.
[SPEAKER_01]: Publications.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you feel full of joy, because this is good work.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dhamma work.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it for a completely wrong reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it because if you were to be put in the middle of the jungle right here, you would probably freak out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if that doesn't worry you, the fact that you're not able to exist anywhere in peace, well, that means you're not really practicing correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much you learn.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how many years you spent
[SPEAKER_01]: Dealing and working around and about the dhamma, you haven't got anything from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, what is... Yeah, because you gave this idea of the right efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon and wholesome, cultivate to wholesome, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the idea comes across as, you've got to be doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing is... Duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go, learn the suttas, you do, you practice... Sīlabhāt, parmasa, holding on to virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not, not just rites and rituals, but duty, the rightful duty, duty of me as a monk, the duty, holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Holding on to it means doing it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, initially, you have to hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why vinaya or sīla comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You hold it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, within that, you're supposed to develop discernments that then makes you let it go, without actually, externally, breaking it, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Letting go of unwholesome and letting go of wholesome, for an ārahant, doesn't mean he goes and becomes wild or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's that sense of duty, yeah, because that's quite risky, because your whole existence as a monk, or as somebody who practices the Buddha's teaching, that you invested 20 years in practicing dhamma, doing retreats or whatever else, there is that sense of duty that has been built up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now letting go of that would basically expose your entire existence since you became a monk, your entire, basically, investment, your entire life.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why many people never do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's like people who try to cross the shore, but are too afraid, and they stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they came to the shore, they found what they need to cross, but they're too afraid to actually start crossing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they just stay in that shore, looking at the other shore they're supposed to go, and they're often happy with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter how much, how many years you spent cultivating and preparing, when you start crossing that river, it's not a guarantee that you will get to the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that is the risk that needs to be taken.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't then say, no, because if I try, I might fail.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I better not try and then just remain concerned about trying, but never do so.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like people who spend their life studying about the dhamma, the scholarly aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean all the scholars do that, but many would do it for those reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up revolving around it, but never really getting through with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Connecting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Collecting information from this teacher and teacherless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Learning about the other show, second-hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is there?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily about doing things full-on with heavy energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the right effort will be determined by the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the right view always comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right effort would be... Again, it's what I was speaking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Make sure... Well, right effort, right intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right effort would come from right intention, which comes from right view, and right view would be making sure the things you're about to do, things you want to do, things you feel you need to do, are not rooted in the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are duties you just have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, that doesn't mean you don't... you shouldn't be mindful of them, or you should feel justified in doing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there are things I need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bottom line is, I always choose to do these things, even if it feels, oh, I need to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you are the one who chooses that to be that which you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you make it effortless?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a feeling, like it's kind of like you doing it, you kind of... Well, no, see...
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentions to do it themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that would be the case for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, that's the thing, like, for putrījana, that would mean, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: These things are just done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on paper, that can be said to be true.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that can be achieved only through fully doing them, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by fully doing them, I mean fully, thoroughly accepting responsibility for every slightest intention you choose to act upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not by kind of finding a state where you forget about your intentions and then things just happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's completely the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might kind of revolve around full circle and externally almost look the same, but there is this, on the inner side, there is this whole trajectory of a set that you actually have to go through with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you go through that kutujana stance by fully accepting responsibility for everything he does.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he chooses to do even things that he has no choice about, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that happen to you, happen to you because you've taken, you've chosen to keep that
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, other things can affect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, misfortunes, accidents, that are not really your fault.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they affect you, well, that's a new why, because you're holding on to the body that is subject to misfortunes, subject to accidents, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you take full responsibility even for things that you cannot possibly control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's so hard and heavy, especially in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, by fully accepting that responsibility, you literally go through that responsibility without abandoning it, and then you find a way out, in case of another hunt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby it... while it does remain, it's a pure individual, pūgala, just the five aggregates free from upādāna, and they just rise and fall until they break apart.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that can be done only when you actually go through with the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, unwholesome needs to be avoided, not just, oh, I keep the precepts, but even mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it's not really... if it's not really morally wrong,
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that I was about to go to library, because I was becoming a bit anxious in my room, so I needed a distraction, that is... that is like, like, you know, shooting yourself in the head, from the point of view of dharma practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a serious mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can... you'll be impeccable externally, perfect monk's form, and never break any rules, but you keep doing things like that, you'll never ever progress in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're just not really looking at the root, at the core of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you said the other day, you're resisting the possibility of suffering, of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when there is no pain, there is a possibility of pain, which hurts you, basically, and you're acting upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're acting because you're afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're acting out of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of going part of
[SPEAKER_00]: And the possibility of pain starts becoming more of a reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole... That's why that sutta that the Buddha said when he was in the... in that jungle, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a fear and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was called fear and dread.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he said, if there would be a fear or an unwholesome state arising while he was walking, he would not change that posture until he dispels the fear first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because whatever he would have done while the fear was present, it would have been rooted in the fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he recognized that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would have been rooted in...
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing unwholesome with sitting down once you've been walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're doing it for the reasons of fear that arose while you were walking, that is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And nobody externally can tell you that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because nobody externally can see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, don't pay much heed to people judging things based on external factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and there's another situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's, you know, monks, or people who are very agreeable, very soft-spoken, and people love them, and people praise them, and it's so great, it's so nice, companions, and they're completely ignorant to two things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you had other people, who were, or monks and people, who were quite hard to live with, unbearable, rude, whatever else, and there were islands.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things pertain basically to personal levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you can see, oh, no, he sat down because he was tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what externally might appear like.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, he sat down because he was afraid of walking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or that monk who was storing rice and then rehydrating it the next day or so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the one because the village was too poor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he didn't want them to waste the food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be starving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's some, some people would say, oh, what kind of monk is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't, doesn't keep that rule and stores food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha did remind him, but not on that personal level, but just on a, from a, from a, like a, like a higher perspective point of view, whereby in the future, doing that,
[SPEAKER_01]: will most likely result in unwholesome, because most people are not actually developed as that monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he was an avarant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then he said, well, still don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The the intention was wholesome, but externally, the vinaya, don't do it, because other people will not be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, of course, to point out that people can, people, petrugians, can praise and blame you for just about anything with that, but praise and blame
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a measure of somebody's attainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If he gets blamed or praised... Not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...it's going to be on the level of... ...of Kutujan.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...of the ludhidus.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they praise you...
[SPEAKER_01]: If Kutujan praises an arahant, he does it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he were to do it for the right reasons, he would be at least Sotāpanna himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would know where the right reasons are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If Kutujan blames the arahant, again, he does it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he were to have the right
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, people just assume, like, you need to have... well, based on your own, you know, life and learning or whatever, you just assume that a wise person, person knows must be some, you know, old man,
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you have in the suttas, you have like... How was that?
[SPEAKER_01]: When the king came to the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The widow was staying in the forest grove, sort of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the king went to see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think King Pasenadi, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And on the way there, he was meeting all these monks, doing walking meditation and just living there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they were all, like, young, in the prime of their youth life.
[SPEAKER_01]: They could still fully enjoy sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they look really happy and healthy.
[SPEAKER_01]: In this remote forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he went to the Buddha, and he was just smitten by this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was just such an experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was praising it, and he said, yeah, because, you know, they don't follow an account of any external observances, and there's something like an account of those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: They follow because they understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, what?
[SPEAKER_01]: You had children, back in the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding the dhamma, obviously, that's quite unlikely today, but it's still possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's this understanding which can't be really measured externally, certainly not by the measure of patujan.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's quite...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's also a useful thing for somebody who knows that he's a patujan and wants to practice to know, because
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't become a victim, then, of sort of developing, oh, no, this is what's right, this is what's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, convince yourself that you, as a pūtugina, know what right is, and what wrong is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were to know that, you wouldn't be a pūtugina.
[SPEAKER_01]: The description of sotāpanna in the suttas is, he knows right as right, and wrong as wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if somebody who knows that he's not a sotāpanna says, no, this is right, and believes that, he's just blocking his own development.
[SPEAKER_01]: You hold that view now, and deep down you know, actually, that you don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly don't have a criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't help by having a judgment.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just a natural thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... thinking is a form of judgment already.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you can help is not develop beliefs on account of your judgment, especially when you know that you don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do have... you can't help it, but you make sure that you find the right judgment, samādhi, the right view, and then you use that as a criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, that becomes the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become that criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: Back to the room, sitting in your room, bored, bored to death.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're sitting there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you want to go downstairs to speak to people, to distract, or some various distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to read a book, a novel.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're sitting there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about all the possibilities, distractions you could have.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, all you have is that pain of boredom, that poor, you know, sensuality curve.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, the best...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to be... if I've seen right effort, what... to be seen that... seen that that has arisen, that boredom is there, and maybe investigating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the right effort would be basically not going, not leaving the room, not acting out of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be the right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: As to what you do on a more particular level, it would be basically, eh... why... ask yourself why is that whole border not going out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it a... why is it... why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it... why is it unwanted?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why does it make you suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize that it's not about you staying in the room or not staying in the room.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about you suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you want to leave the room.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when I get distracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is the core of dhamma, suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dukkha and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why do I don't want to be touched by the unpleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why, by default, I resist that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why, by default, I act upon it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why I take it for granted that I must run away from this feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all I have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: The tiny little thorn needs to be pulled out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a tiny little resistance to pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You pull that out, you won't be touched by anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you certainly won't be pulling anything out if you're running away whenever these things and pressure arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you act upon distractions, leave the room, pretend, find dutiful and meaningful sort of things that end up being just distractions or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's my duty to spread the dhamma and, you know, do the publication.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, your duty is to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whatever you do, or at least talk about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, whatever you do will be coming out of the right view, even if externally people don't recognize it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not your concern.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's a major need for, you know, sitting there, if you're in pain, this fearlessness you need to have, this fearlessness... Basically, the moment, like, the moment you stop fearing the pain, you can get up and leave, if you want to do that, because it won't be rooted in acting out of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha wanted to sit down, but he made sure he removed the fear and then he sat down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't possibly not do anything for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just want to make sure that it's never ever rooted again in unwholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, there will be quickly remedied.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, you might just have to sit in the room and endure it for days.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, that won't last forever either, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about taking for granted the resistance to unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: That needs to be uprooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: That tiny little thing needs to be pulled out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then all the other puss and infection on account of it will... it's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually it will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not being, like, you know, infected anymore by that
[SPEAKER_00]: That's sort of the... the craving for the pleasant, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You crave for pleasure, because basically not having enough of that pleasure is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your whole life revolves around fear of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even people who are going to subject themselves to pain, to prove themselves that they're not afraid of pain, they need to prove themselves, because underneath that, they're afraid of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they try to override it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, if you're afraid of pain, then you might start practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might, you know, that's my reason for becoming a monk or... That is THE reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I am... That is the sole reason, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am... like when a layman reflects before he goes forth in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Prey.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm being hunted, so I'm... nothing got me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that I feel like I'm a prey to this suffering means the hunter is there, always, and he might pounce at any moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't necessarily pounce, but you recognize that you are actually a prey in this field, when there are, you know, serious carnivores.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if they don't kill you, the fact that they might kill you, that is suffering in itself, that concern, that fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, I am subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I don't necessarily suffer, but I recognize that if suffering does land, at some point, I'm subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't be able to prevent that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might be able to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As an aftermath, in hindsight, I might be able to resolve it, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that you were touched in the first place, that is THE problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: One and only.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing he teaches, the only thing he could possibly teach, is suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything else is done because of that, whether people know it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You pursue pleasure because not having enough of it is not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, you realize you never have enough of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you keep pursuing more.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's just more and more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You run away from pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're running away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you avoided it temporarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's like temporary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Temporary means there's obviously no greater perspective than the wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because scratching your itch temporarily relieves you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the long run, it makes you much more infected and worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people would say that people are much more distracted nowadays, but, you know, with phones or whatever, Internet, I don't believe that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a different type.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's just that it's more proliferated, but the roots were the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The roots of distraction, they're rooted in the same things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people today are more frivolous, probably more divorced from the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that proliferation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that nature is still there, which means the roots of the distractions are still the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you want to get things going quick, you know, you want to start to practice, you want to see the truth, understand, be able to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Precepts, restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts, restraint, and then we'll show you the fear quite quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Put down your phone, switch off the internet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Put down your phone, switch off the internet.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're a layman, well, try and be a celibate, if not, try and keep the third precept.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't eat like a pig.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, start practicing restraint in regard to your senses, and all these things will be revealed very quickly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then,
[SPEAKER_01]: And be very careful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't start holding views on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And holding views on account of it is what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, you know that you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you accepted that what you're doing now is the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you develop a belief that this is the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still don't know for yourself that it's the right thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said that, you know, monks can live withdrawn from sensuality, physically and even mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, they end up arguing and debating and holding on to views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, māra still controls them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, one thing at a time, you know, you can't be dealing with the views,
[SPEAKER_01]: If your behavior is still unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restrain behavior, don't pursue distractions, and then endure the views for a while, and then they'll become apparent, and you'll know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you basically, again, what I'm saying, you stop rooting them in unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, or, you can't help but having views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you just want to know, make sure that you know that when you have views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know that these are inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: The views are inevitable, but all I... what I can do is not hold to them blindly to such an extent that I believe, even if it's about the sīla and the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's still no justification to hold the views in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, abandoning views.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a view that nothing pleases me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and that view pleases you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what people say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you don't hold to any fixed views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that is a fixed view that you clearly hold on to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't hold to views by recognizing that views are inevitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you do have views, but you don't hold to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what it's meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean, like, don't hold to views, like, not actually have any views.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the right view is a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just replaces the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the most you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's all you can do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just replace your wrong views with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will lead you to the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your wrong intention for the rise, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, intentions... because they're all intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll never intend anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll never do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll never leave this room for the rest of my life, because everything is bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, that's your intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's something you're clearly doing, you're clearly intending, clearly performing, and you're fully not aware of.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that view, in that sutta, that says...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's in Majjhima, 74,
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing pleases me, he says there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you oppose to this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you oppose to denunciation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you, you, you, you would, you would basically, uh, nothing pleases me.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't commit to any other, more particular view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you know, there is that one that you need to deal with.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, I don't, I'm not obsessed with existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that is, you're not, you're not pulled into it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the only reason you were pulled into it was because you were acting out of fear of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were a prey to suffering and you were just doing what prey does.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, there might be a hunter behind this tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know, why are you dressed around?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, when you know as a child, you know, something, you might feel something's chasing you, as a kid, in the dark or whatever, and then you start running out of fear, get quicker to your home.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you give in to running, then you become even more afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if there's nothing chasing you, once you give in to running, you'll need to run even faster.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like an avalanche that you're responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: A flood, a floodgate that you open.